[
    {
        "question": "",
        "answer": "This is the first and most common interview question which is asked in every interview. Even you are well known for it; it is the most difficult question to answer. This is because it puts all the pressure on the candidate, and if he/she is not confident, then the condition becomes more adverse. The interviewer asks this question to check how confident you are and how you present yourself. Don't explain all your life's story here. You have to concentrate on sharing a bit about your strengths that build the platform for further discussion about your suitability for the job opening.\nTo answer this question, the candidate has to be quick and not take much time to overthink how he/she should answer this question? It would be best if you started your answer by giving a small briefing of your educational and professional qualifications, family background, career path and how you ended up in this interview, applying for this job. You should express your views so that the interviewer gets curious and takes an interest in knowing more about you.\nMost Important Tips:\nADVERTISEMENT\nADVERTISEMENT\nKeep your introduction short and precise.\nDon't narrate what you have already mentioned on your CV.\nFocus more on talking about your achievements, certifications and learning.\nFor more details: https://www.javatpoint.com/job-interview-questions",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "interview-questions-for-freshers"
    },
    {
        "question": "2) What do you know about our company?",
        "answer": "This question is generally asked by the interviewer or hiring manager at the beginning of the conversation to know how much you are aware of the organization where you want to work. The best way to tackle this interview question is to do proper research about the company where you will face the interview. Read online about the company's latest updates, understand its business, and above all, read the job description thoroughly.\nMost Important Tips:\nVisit the company's website to read 'About Us', its mission-vision, history, values, achievements, products & services, clients, and key people.\nCheck the company's social presence on popular platforms such as LinkedIn, Facebook, and Twitter to get a better understanding of the latest updates about the company.\nSearch Company related news on Google to get company reviews and all.\nSample Answer:\nABC is one of the fastest growing startups in the IT industry in India today. I have seen the company's success stories recently published on LinkedIn and various other press releases and they are just fabulous. Although the company is founded just 4 years ago but its success is commendable. I have also read the company's 'about us' on the official website and it's great to know how quickly it is growing. It will be my pleasure to be a part of such a growing company and learn more.",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "interview-questions-for-freshers"
    },
    {
        "question": "3) How did you hear about this job?",
        "answer": "The interviewer asks this question to see the candidate's interest in the company and job profile. Generally, the candidates answer this question by saying I have got the notification through some job portal or website where I have applied.\nYou can also say that I desired to work for this company, so I have checked on its official website where I see the job openings, and I am here. If you know any employee of the company who has advised you to apply to this company, this would be a good time to mention his or her name.",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "interview-questions-for-freshers"
    },
    {
        "question": "4) Why do you want to work here? / Why do you want to work with this company?",
        "answer": "This is a very common interview question that companies asked to fresher to know what they want and how much they know about the company they are applying for. The candidates are always recommended to study and know about the company's background, values, operations, services, and other important details before appearing for the interview.\nMost Important Tips:\nThe candidates must be aware of the company's values and ethics and correlate their career goals with the same.\nThe candidates should state how working with the company can help them to enhance their skills and knowledge.",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "interview-questions-for-freshers"
    },
    {
        "question": "5) Do you think that final examination marks reflect your potential?",
        "answer": "This question can surprise you, and you will think about how to answer this question. The interviewer asks this question to check your presence of mind, ability to justify your examination score and extracurricular activities. By asking this question, the interviewer wants to judge you based on your other skills such as hobbies, extracurricular skills etc., rather than your examination marks.\nIt would be best if you did not answer this question in a simple, straightforward way. Try to answer it in the following way:\nIf we talk about exam scores, then it shows how well I performed on that specific examination day. Well, it does not completely show my overall potential. But, yes, there is a benefit of scoring good marks in semester exams. At that time, it was a great confidence booster and enhanced me through the services I appeared. Along with marks, other extracurricular activities are also important. They help us to furnish our skills which increase our potential to work harder and become successful in life.",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "interview-questions-for-freshers"
    },
    {
        "question": "6) Why should we hire you?",
        "answer": "This is a very tricky interview question. By this question, the interviewer wants to judge your ability to pitch your skills and convincing power. This interview question provides you an opportunity to show the interviewer your willingness for the job. You can explain why you are the most suitable for this role.\nThe best way to answer this interview question is to talk about your skills and strengths required for this job role, and you possess them. You can also share some examples of how you managed a few projects or important assignments in your college that reflect your strengths.\nMost Important Tips:\nShare your strengths and skills that are relevant to the job description, but keep it short.\nIf the interviewer wants to know more about particular instances, explain in detail to validate your points.",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "interview-questions-for-freshers"
    },
    {
        "question": "7) How do you think you will fit in this role?",
        "answer": "This question is asked to check if the candidate clearly understands the company's job responsibilities and the functional area. While answering this question, you need to explain to the interviewer that you know well the job responsibilities and know how to perform well.\nA good sample answer should be like this:\nI think I am one of the best candidates for this job. I will fit in this job role as what I have learned so far about the role and the company, I find myself a good way fit when it comes to needs from both the ends. It makes me inspired to think about getting to know the team and all other things I can learn and contribute towards the company.",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "interview-questions-for-freshers"
    },
    {
        "question": "8) What do you expect from your reporting manager?",
        "answer": "This is one of the most important questions for a fresher candidate to answer. He/she is completely new to the corporate culture and doesn't know anything about working ethics. The working atmosphere of corporates is completely different from college life. People face a lot of difficulties while working for companies. So, while answering such questions, you need to be confident and specific with your words. You can say that the words of managers are always for the benefit of the company. I think it will positively help me work better.",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "interview-questions-for-freshers"
    },
    {
        "question": "9) Where Do You See Yourself In 5 Years?",
        "answer": "This is one of the most difficult interview questions for a fresher candidate. When you face your first job interview, you are more concerned about your first year of the job and planning for such a long time seems formidable to many freshers. The interviewer asks this question mainly to see your willingness to stay longer with the company. The second reason may be to ask this question is to see how well planned you are about your career goals and life.\nMost Important Tips:\nDo give any clue that you want this job to gain experience, and then you wish for something bigger shortly.\nYour answer should align with the current job role. Your long-term goal is also relevant to the company profile. It will show your interest in the company.",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "interview-questions-for-freshers"
    },
    {
        "question": "10) What are your salary expectations?",
        "answer": "As a fresher, it is very rare that you will face this interview question. The companies already have a fixed package for the fresher. But, suppose if you asked this question, then the best way is to cope with this question is to do some research in advance so that you can confidently tell a reasonable range.\nMost Important Tips:\nDon't ask for either a too less or too high salary package.\nIf you don't have any idea about a reasonable salary for the job role, you can say that I will accept the package as per industry standards.",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "interview-questions-for-freshers"
    },
    {
        "question": "11) What are your greatest strengths?",
        "answer": "This is an important interview question that fresher candidates generally face. The main motive behind asking this question is to see and understand how much you know about yourself and how confident you are about your strengths or positive points. By asking this question, the employer analyzes your strengths for the job role and checks if you are tough enough to face the challenges in the job profile.\nThe best way to answer this question is to share your positive points and strengths related to the job. Always be confident while answering any question related to it. In the end, you can also say that you are a quick learner and very adaptive. It adds value to your strengths.\nMost important Tips:\nStay positive and confident. If you confidently say that \"I am a very positive and optimistic person\", it will also be good enough.\n\nYou can also change this as per the requirement of the company interview.\nSample Examples:\nSir, I think my greatest strength is my ability to learn things quickly. In the 3rd year of my college, I had to represent my college in an inter college science exhibition, and I was introduced to the team at the very last minute. I understand our exhibits and artifacts quickly and present my team in the exhibition successfully.\nMy greatest strength is my positive attitude. It was our final year college project when there has been couple of times, our idea was not falling in place and the results were negative. I had to believe and think positively and keep my team motivated to persist on our idea, and finally we got the desired result.",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "interview-questions-for-freshers"
    },
    {
        "question": "12) What are your weaknesses?",
        "answer": "This is a critical question where you have to share your weaknesses with your hiring manager. This is never recommended to say that you do not have any weakness as it sounds arrogant. Then, how to express your weak points also in a positive way that can impress the interviewer.\nThe best way to answer this question is to tell a weakness to the interviewer that doesn't impact your current job role. For example, if you are afraid to watch horror movies alone, it can be your weakness. It also doesn't relate to your job role.\nMost Important Tips:\nDon't brag about the strengths and skills that you cannot justify.\nIt would be best if you always prepared yourself to elaborate on your strengths and weaknesses with some quick examples.",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "interview-questions-for-freshers"
    },
    {
        "question": "13) What are your hobbies?",
        "answer": "Generally, this is a must asked interview question to a fresher candidate. By asking this question, the interviewer tries to check your personality, energy level, and how to fit you for its culture.\nThe best way to answer this question is to share something that enhances your skills, such as traveling, reading science & technology books and magazines, meeting new people etc. You can also share some generic hobbies such as some sports or jogging, exercise etc. They reflect that you are an active person.\nSome Important Tips:\nDon't share hobbies that can have a bad impact, such as online betting and gambling.\nYou can share a mix of personal and professional interests and hobbies. It shows that you are a balanced person in life.",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "interview-questions-for-freshers"
    },
    {
        "question": "14) What can you do for us that other candidates can't?",
        "answer": "Here, you can emphasize what makes you unique. You can state your greatest strengths, positive points, and extra-curricular activities that could help you do better in this job or any prior internship experience related to this job.\nThe interviewer asks this question to see your experiences, skills and traits. Example of a good sample answer:\nSir, I have a unique combination of strong technical skills and the ability to build strong customer relationships. I have a 6-month internship experience at the XYZ Company. This will help me use my knowledge and experience to do better in this job.",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "interview-questions-for-freshers"
    },
    {
        "question": "15) What are three positive things your last boss would say about you?",
        "answer": "This question is asked to see what your thinking about your previous employer is. It also shows how your relationship with peers and your boss was. Suppose you are a fresher and you have just a 3-month internship experience at a company. The best way to answer this question is to brag about yourself through someone else's words: \"My boss has told me that I am the best intern he has ever had. He knows he can rely on me, and he likes my sense of humor.\"",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "interview-questions-for-freshers"
    },
    {
        "question": "16) When were you most satisfied with your job? / What motivates you most in a job?",
        "answer": "By asking this question, the interviewer wants to know what motivates you the most. You can give an example of your project, your examination or any other function when you were excited, and the interviewer will get an idea of your preferences and what he/she wants to hear.\nA good sample answer should be like this:\nIn my college, I was working voluntarily for an NGO which provided books and cloths to the poor children. At that time, I was very satisfied in that work, because I worked directly with the crushed and deprived children of the country and solved their problems. That is a memorable and pleasant task I have done while my under graduation.",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "interview-questions-for-freshers"
    },
    {
        "question": "17) Who is your inspiration in your life? / Who is the most inspiring person in your life?",
        "answer": "The interviewer asks this question to check how you see or take things in your life. You can answer this question with a name that greatly impacts your life or your thinking. If you take a name, you have some valid reasons and explain why he/she is the most inspiring person for you.\nSome good sample examples are given below:\nExample 1: \"I find inspiration in a variety of people and things. I would have to say that the person who has most greatly inspired me has been my father. He always had a smile on his face no matter how hard he worked or how bad his day was passed. He loved everyone. He has always thought me to not worry about my weakness and take most advantage of my strengths. This has developed a lot of confidence in me during difficult times. I try to live like he did, as much as I can.\"\nExample 2: \"My greatest inspiration is Rahul Dravid. I have a lot of reasons to like him such as he had a humble upbringing and his hard work took him to the greatest heights in the world of cricket. He still keeps himself rooted and stays humble. I also believe in hard work and humility\".\nExample 3: \"I am greatly inspired by the Dabbawalas of Mumbai. Many of them have hectic lives, mouths to feed, and less than impressive education. They overcome their hardships and come to work every day to make life better for themselves and their children as well as a lot of employees in many offices in Mumbai.\"\nExample 4: Though many industry leaders inspire me, I would have to say that my greatest inspiration comes from my mother, who always taught me to stay focused and goal-oriented, no matter the obstacles that come my way. Her way of thinking and teaching has greatly improved my character.\"",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "interview-questions-for-freshers"
    },
    {
        "question": "18) Are you willing to change your role and profile when required for the project? / Do you have any issue to change your role or profile as the company requires in the future?",
        "answer": "As a fresher, the company wants to choose the candidates who are flexible for anything. Flexibility is much required when you are a fresher.\nBy answering this question, you need to expose that you are flexible and ready to learn. If you say that you are flexible, it doesn't necessarily mean you will be forced into things you don't like. It just shows your positive attitude to learn and try new things.\nA good sample answer should be like this:\nYes, definitely sir. As a fresher, I want to learn as much things as possible. I believe that if I get different roles and profiles, they only help me to learn and grow more",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "interview-questions-for-freshers"
    },
    {
        "question": "19) Are you ready /flexible to relocate in the future?",
        "answer": "As a fresher, it is always better to be ready for relocation as long as you do not have any compelling reasons. It is very normal in the IT industry. They work on a global operation model and have offices located at several locations. If the company finds the need for your skills at a particular location, they can relocate you there.\nBeing a fresher, you should be flexible enough to suit the staffing need of the company. It is also easy for a company to move a fresher on short notice because they have less baggage (for example, single). This applies to a foreign country placement also. So, if you deny a relocation means, you are saying \"No\" to an onsite opportunity as well.\nA good sample answer should be like this:\nExample 1: \"Yes, most definitely. I don't have any issue to relocate because being at different locations can help me to learn about new culture and people.\"\nExample 2: \"Yes, I don't have any problem in relocation. It is always better to learn experience than being around with same environment and people.\"",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "interview-questions-for-freshers"
    },
    {
        "question": "20) Are you flexible with timings? / Do you have any issues if you have to work in night shift?",
        "answer": "If you are applying for a job that requires shift work, you can expect to face some questions about your flexibility about changing this schedule. This question is asked to check about your flexibility in the timing of your job hours. There are always some challenges in working in shifts. The employers are well aware of these challenges and look to hire people who can handle this unpredictability.\nThe same above answer applies here. Being a fresher, the company assumes that you have not any issue with the timings. If you have any genuine issue or problem to work in the night or early morning shifts, you can mention here. Remember that your negative answer might slightly reduce your chance of getting the job. Suppose the company has some foreign clients and needs you to work the night shift, then the company prefers the candidate who has no issue with timing.\nExamples of best sample answers:\nExample 1: Absolutely, sir. I don't have any issues with shift changes. I live alone, and I don't mind if the company allows me night or early morning shifts.\nExample 2: I am available to work any shift as you require. I must be there when the company needs me.\nExample 3: If there is an urgent need or an emergency, I'll work whatever shifts the company asks me to do. The growth of the company is directly proportional to the employee's success.\nExample 4: I will work whatever shift is required because I feel responsible for the company to complete the necessary work.\nExample 5: I am only available during regular business hours as there is an elderly family member who I need to care for during other times. But if the company needs me in the case of an urgent situation, then I will be available.\nExample 6: As a girl, I am not comfortable with night shifts due to safety concerns, but I am happy to work any other shift as needed.\nExample 7: I would be happy to work night and weekend shifts if the company provides me a cab facility and have a proper security guard in place.",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "interview-questions-for-freshers"
    },
    {
        "question": "21) Do you want to pursue higher education?",
        "answer": "If you have an immediate plan for higher education seriously, it is good to say so. If you are unsure (maybe or may not be), you can answer like the following:\nExample 1: \"I am interested in higher studies, but not immediately. I want to start my career and then look for higher studies after gaining some experience in this field.\nExample 2: \"Yes, but not immediately. After getting some experience in my field, I will do an MBA or VLSI engineering masters, depending on which will be more beneficial for my line of work.\"\nSome companies support and provide incentives to their employees for higher studies. If you know that your employer company has any such programs, you can align your answer accordingly.",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "interview-questions-for-freshers"
    },
    {
        "question": "22) What are your expectations from your first job?",
        "answer": "To answer this question, you can quote a simple vision or strategy about the company you like most. The most important expectation for a fresher is to \"Learn,\" which most companies expect from you. You can also say that you want to place yourself within the corporate world, pay off your education loan, contribute to society, etc.\nThe best possible answers are:\nExample 1: \"I have had lot of studies during my college years, but mostly theoretical leanings. So, my first expectation from my first job would be to learn how all these are applied in a practical and industrial way. I also want to be a part of the corporate culture and be a good asset for the company.\"\n\nExample 2: \" Sir, this is my first job and I consider this as an extension of my studies only. This is more like a practical class for me. Here, I want to learn new technologies, learn how the corporate world works, be the part of a big energetic team and contribute to the projects. I also want to develop my soft skills to make a good place in this tough and challenging corporate life in future.\"",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "interview-questions-for-freshers"
    },
    {
        "question": "23) Do you have any questions for us?",
        "answer": "This is probably the last interview question where the interviewer leaves scope for you to clear your doubts. Generally, fresher hesitates to ask the interviewer questions, but it is considered good practice to ask the interviewer some relevant questions. It shows that you are a confident and focused person who is interested in the job.\nYou should prepare at least 3 or 4 questions in mind to ask at the end of the interview. It creates a positive impact.\nSome Important Tips:\nAsk intelligent questions that show your curiosity to know more about the company, its policies, people, any specific skill you need to acquire for the given role, etc.\nDon't ask irrelevant questions such as the duration of lunch hours, how often the company organizes parties, or how soon you will be promoted to the next level.",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "interview-questions-for-freshers"
    }
]